Guide to Theodore Bonin Collection on Downtown Artists MSS.486
Fales Library and Special Collections
Theodore Bonin Collection on Downtown Artists
1981-1998
Fales Library and Special Collections
Bonin, Theodore
MSS.486
3 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, and 2 oversize folders
This collection was assembled by gallery owner Theodore Bonin, containing 61 artworks and publications from over 20 artists including Tom Otterness, Lisa Bowman, Judy Rifka, Janine Antoni, and Luis Frangella, who were active in New York's downtown art scene during the 1980s and 1990s. Artwork mediums include hand colored and painted works on paper, wood sculpture, ceramic sculptures, prints, and assemblages.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains 61 artworks and publications, accumulated by Theodore Bonin over many years, from over 20 artists including Tom Otterness, Lisa Bowman, Judy Rifka, Janine Antoni, and Luis Frangella, who were active in New York's downtown art scene during the 1980s and 1990s. Artwork media represented in this collection include painted or drawn works on paper, wood sculpture, ceramic sculptures, prints, and assemblages, all produced during the 1980s and 1990s. This collection illustrates popular mediums and subject matter in artworks in this community of artists in New York.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Theodore Bonin in December, 2016; the accession number associated with this gift is 2017.031.
Arrangement
Materials have been intellectually arranged in the inventory by an archivist following the donor's alphabetical list by artists' last name, followed by publications. Physically the material was boxed together according to size.
Biographical Note
Theodore Bonin is an art collector and part owner of Alexander and Bonin, a New York art gallery established in 1995, whose primary purpose is to represent and support the work of emerging, mid-career, and established international contemporary artists.
Artists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Painting.; woodcuts (prints); Art, American -- 20th century; Drawings, pen and ink.; Photographic prints.; Announcements.; Invitations.; Drawings (visual works); Artists and community -- New York (State) -- New York; Rifka, Judy, 1945-; Frangella, Luis, 1944-1990; Goodman, Ken; Lanigan-Schmidt, Thomas; Momenta Art (Organization); Nechvatal, Joseph; Otterness, Tom, 1952-
- Allen, Bill. Framed and colored poem "Birds Fish People Mammals", circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bowman, Lisa. Hand painted gallery show announcement for "Fiction/Non Fiction", Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Candyass and Aura Rosenberg. Photograph, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Candyass. "Barfbag/shopping bag", 1991 (Folder 13 Right)
- Dix/Dix. (ROMA NAPOLI & J.J. DOW JONES) "Bouquet Fleuri", 1985 (Box Shared Fales 078, Folder 2)
- Elwell, Chip. Untitled red dragon woodblock print holiday card, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Fawbush, Joe and Tommy Jones. Relief print Christmas star card, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Frangella, Luis. Two untitled crayon drawings, circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Gilbert, Ame. "Baby" (painted wood), Undated (Box 3, Item 1)
- Goodman, Ken. 16 untitled drawings on tissue paper, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Green, Denise. "Adam" (ink and pencil on paper, 11-1/4 x 9") and exhibition installation photograph, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Lanigan-Schmidt, Thomas. "School of Art" (lithograph, 12x12" signed ed: 200), 1986 (Box Shared Fales 078, Folder 2)
- Lanigan-Schmidt, Thomas. Invitation to "Hidden Treasure" exhibit at Holly Solomon, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Lovett/Codagnone. Photograph with parents(?), Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Momenta Art. Envelope "The Art of Self Defense and Revenge." Contains 12 female artists' material, including Janine Antoni with "Fuck off Red", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Momenta Art. Envelope "…Its Really Hard." Contains 9 male artists' works, including Jim Hodges, Tony Feher, and Lucky DeBellevue, circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Nechvatal, Joseph. "Diabolos Incarnatus" (tari red paper, 20x18-1/4 AP 1/5) and untitled blue plastic silkscreen piece, 1984-1985
- Otterness, Tom. Two plaques with figures (Skoto gallery), Undated (Box 3, Item 2)
- Rifka, Judith. Five "plastics" pieces (dog piece is from Amore Store); "Square Dress" (3 drawings), Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Rifka, Judith. Collectiva Internationale ARTPAK includes Haring, Nadin; Brooke Alexander exhibit installation photograph; Catalogue, "The Greatest Show on Earth", 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
- Schneeman, George. Calendar 309/485, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Tower, Cindy. "Valentine" (painted wood piece), Undated (Box 2, Item 1)
- Winter, Robin. "White Black" (pencil, india ink and white chalk on paper), and envelope with "xmas 1990" drawing, signed, 1981, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Publication. Cara Perlman. "Fingerpaint Portraits." Appearances Press, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Publication. Stewart Hitch. ArtExtreme magazine, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)